Guide to the Cedric N. Chatterley Photographs, 1983-2013 and undated RL.00219
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Spencer, South Dakota Series, 1998-2008, 7 boxes; 268 prints
  - 11x14 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints, 192 prints
    - Parishoner holding pieces of stained glass window found after the Trinity Lutheran Church was destroyed by the May 30, 1998 tornado, Spencer, after Sunday services had ended on what remained of the church, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 28)
    - Organized volunteers (who stayed for several days) preparing baked beans for workers and volunteers in a tent on Sunday, downtown Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 29)
    - Orrie Townsend standing on the second story of his house and pointing to the foundation where his house stood the day before the May 30th tornado, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 30)
      He and his wife were not home at the time. Their house was built in the 1980s.
    - Self-portrait in abandoned chair in front of Orrie Townsend's house, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 31)
      (Henry operating equipment nearby did not allow me to hear the timer on my camera, thus causing the awkward moment.)
    - Nancy Webb watching the razing of her and Lloyd's house following the May 30, 1998 tornado, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 32)
      Nancy was the only person I knew who stood and witnessed their home being razed. I introduced myself shortly after making this image.
    - Volunteers from the Federated Church of God in Des Moines, Iowa placing donated clothing in a drive-away storage bin, in the parking lot of the National Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 35)
      Donated items streamed in for days following the May 30, 1998 tornado. Most of the items were not taken.
    - Downtown Spencer facing south, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 36)
      The pile of rubble in the distance is one of two such heaps, increasing by the day. Near the end of June, both piles will be set on fire.
    - Abandoned engine, Spencer, June 1999 (Box 21, Print 37)
    - Spencer from the top of the heavily damaged grain elevator that was knocked down and razed weeks later, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 38)
    - Riding with Bernie Opland, heading south on Interstate 29 towards Sioux City, Iowa, just south of Sioux Falls, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 39)
      His truck was loaded with cars he had crushed after the Spencer tornado.
    - Bernie Opland un-chaining cars he crushed in Spencer, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 40)
      Opland and I were leaving the crushed cars at a recycling yard in Sioux City, Iowa. Bernie lived near Baltic, South Dakota.
    - Worker pulling cars off Bernie Opland's flat bed truck at a metal recycling business in Sioux City, Iowa, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 41)
      Bernie crushed these cars in Spencer following the May 30, 1998 tornado. This load was one of several loads.
    - Downtown Spencer through rain on my car window, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 43)
      The dog is fake.
    - Part of the urban planning meeting held for Spencer residents in the McCook County High School gymnasium, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 45)
      The books on the left were being sold by Salvation Army Volunteers. The display board on the right listed all the families and home sites affected by the May 30th tornado. Urban planners from Sioux Falls had suggested that those who rebuild in Spencer try and do so by possibly trading their property and building closer together. Believing that not everybody in Spencer would rebuild, they wanted to avoid large gaps between homes. The idea was roundly rejected by those who planned to stay.
    - Urban planners from Sioux Falls unveiling plans to rebuild Spencer, McCook County High School gymnasium, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 46)
      This was the very last image I made with the original Ilford HP5 from the 100 foot bulk rolls.
    - Hallway at the National Guard Amory, Salem, South Dakota, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 47)
      The six brothers and sisters are in reference to the six deaths during the tornado in Spencer on May 30, 1998.
    - Bernie Opland (who contracted with Spencer to crush cars after the tornado) having a lunch prepared and distributed by the Red Cross, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 48)
    - From the back window of my father's 1981 Volkswagen pickup, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 49)
      I would park at the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Rd 431 and work or hitchhike into Spencer during the first 10 days or so following the May 30th tornado. I did not know at the time that Dave and Mary Twedt owned this property, having only met them briefly a few days after the tornado destroyed their home in Spencer. The driver is an unidentified Spencer resident with a truckload of furniture salvaged during the thunderstorm.
    - A small part of the clothing that had been recovered by volunteers in Spencer piled up in the Springfield State Corrections Center near Yankton, South Dakota, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 50)
      Inmates will launder and fold the clothing and it will be offered to Spencer residents in July.
    - Crews digging one of two pits to "bury" Spencer, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 51)
      This was the West pit.
    - One of two massive piles of what was razed in Spencer following the May 30 tornado, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 52)
      The pile was at the southeast edge of town and made from the top of the grain elevator.
      This image was made with a telephoto lens.
    - Volunteers working in the Natinal Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, June 1998 (Box 21, Print 53)
      Donated items streamed in for days following the F-4 tornado that hit Spencer 10 miles west. Most items were not used and they were eventually sent to various organizations like the Slavation Army.
    - Dave and Mary Twedt, Independence Day, 1998 (Box 21, Print 55)
      After having their home in Spencer destroyed by a F-4 tornado, they have decided to rebuild their commercial property into a home 1/2 mile south of town. This was once the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge. Legend has it that an artist traveling through sometime in the 1950s painted the scenic mural on the wall in exchange for several days stay in the adjoining motel. I tried to talk Dave into letting the mural remain in what would become their living room. Consideration was given but the mural fell to the Twedts' hammers the following week. Over the month of July, the Twedts and I filled several dumpster loads in the gutting process of this property.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt taking a break during the construction of their home, McCook County, South Dakota, at the intersection of Highway 38 and County Road 431, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 56)
      Dave is watchful of gathering storm clouds.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt, Gilbert Schuchardt and Danny Stone in front of Gilbert's home currently under construction in central Spencer, facing southwest, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 57)
      The Twedts and I used to take a daily cruise through town as a way to take a break from working on their home. Dave called these little rides into town as "dress codes" or "inspecting the dress code" out of a tongue-in-cheek poke at the recent building code enforcements that followed the tornado. Dave was very vocal about the local politics.
    - Mary Twedt soon after finding a cushion for her patio furniture that had been missing since the tornado, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 58)
      They had been cruising around Spencer one day in mid-July and saw it laying near the monument that had been placed to remember the Spencer School.
    - Dave Twedt taking a break and Mary Twedt sweeping in what will be the kitchen of their new home, the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 59)
      The Twedts are rebuilding what once was the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge. Dave bought this property less than one mile south of Spencer in 1986, several years before they bought a home in Spencer Proper.
    - Dave Twedt at work in the basement of what was once the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge, the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 60)
    - Dave and Mary Twedt visiting the building site of their friends' Gilbert and JoAnne (right image) and the vacant lot where their house had been just a few blocks away (left image), Spencer 1998 (Box 21, Print 61)
    - Mary Twedt riding on the pickup tailgate while Dave drives, 1/2 mile outside of Spencer, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 62)
      The Twedts and I were on our way to burn trash at the end of the property. Mary is looking north towards Spencer.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt surveying the items recovered by the 5,000 volunteers who had combed Spencer, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 63)
      5 days after a F-4 tornado destroyed 75% of the town organized volunteers then cleaned recovered items and set them on tables in the McCook County High School gym. The clothes that had been recovered were taken to the Springfield State Prison near Yankton where they were laundered in 200 pound capacity machines. Other items were cleaned and sorted by local organizations. I saw several people, including Dave and Mary, pick up and examine items that had been theirs prior to the tornado, then return them to the table. Dave said, "Some things are better left alone..." Upon walking into the gym for the first time, Nancy Webb said, "This is worse than the tornado." Many folks stood over the tables that had been covered with photographs from a period of at least 100 years and wept openly. It was the most powerful photo exhibit I had ever witnessed.
    - Mary Twedt holding three family photographs: Jessica (her and Dave's daughter) as a toddler in a high chair, Dave Twedt at age 4, and Mary at about 18 months, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 64)
      Mary is wrapped in a quilt made by her grandmother. The Twedts and I were in the McCook Central High School gym where all the items recovered after the tornado by volunteers had been set out. There were 7-8 tables of nothing but photographs. The quilt and these photographs were among the many items that filled the gymnasium.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt in the McCook Cental High School gymnasium, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 65)
      Clothing and objects that had been picked up by volunteers after the tornado were stacked on tables for Spencer residents. Over 5,000 volunteers combed Spencer on June 5, filling plastic bags with clothing, kitchen appliances, utensils, and many personal items. More than 7 tables were completely covered with carefully cleaned photographs. Mary is holding a quilt made by her grandmother.
    - Mary Twedt holding photographs that had been recovered by volunteers who combed Spencer following the March 30th tornado, McCook County High School gymnasium, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 66)
      There were 7 tables of photographs laid edge to edge.
    - Mary Twedt holding up a can of beer to celebrate flowing water from the well, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 67)
      The Twedts had been without running water for 45 days following the tornado. The Twedts are now rebuilding commercial property into a home. The property was once the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge with several hotel rooms. Dave Twedt bought this property in 1986, several years before they bought their home in Spencer about 1/2 mile to the north. The Twedts and I filled the dumpster (right) more than 3 times with material during the "gutting" process. The Twedts lived in the camper trailer for 6 months while working on their home.
    - Delphia Stuby with her granddaughter, Kallie Kennedy Rogers, on Delphia's lot in northwest Spencer, July 30, 1998 (Box 21, Print 68)
      Kallie's father, Ed Rogers, dressed in white. Delphia's new home was built by South Dakota State Penitentiary inmates on site at the Springfield prison yard near Yankton. The interior is 768 sq ft, two bedrooms, one bath. Applicants must be 62 or older, or 18 with disability. The cost was $19,400, including delivery. Five of these homes were purchased in 1998/99 by families displaced by the tornado, three of which were placed in Spencer. Although Kallie and her parents moved to Michigan, Delphia said later, "Kallie is fifth generation Spencer."
    - Lloyd Webb during a break while working to re-hab Nancy Webb's childhood farmhouse, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, July, 1998 (Box 21, Print 69)
      The Webb's house in Spencer proper was destroyed after receiving heavy tornado damage on May 30, 1998. They decided to use the insurance money to rebuild the farmhouse.
      Selenium toned gelatin silver print--two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Suzy Webb with bag of candy, Bridgette watches. Near the family farmhouse, July 1998 (Box 21, Print 70)
      McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer.
    - Lloyd, Suzy and Nancy Webb inspect an antique farm wagon at an auction a few miles west of Spencer, South Dakota, September, 1999. (Box 21, Print 71)
      They bought the wagon and later towed it home. I followed. The steel wheels made a wonderful noise rolling on the asphalt.
    - Lloyd Webb and I digging post-holes to put up barbed wire fencing. Horse bones at center and right of image, the north pasture on the family farm, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, September, 1998 (Box 21, Print 72)
    - Dave Twedt covered with insulation during the rebuilding of their commercial property at the corner of Highway 38 and County Road 431. About 1/2 mile south of Spencer, South Dakota, September, 1998 (Box 21, Print 73)
    - Mary Twedt sitting in the front passenger seat of their car, September, 1998 (Box 21, Print 74)
      She and Dave passing the vacant lot where their house had been just a few months earlier in Spencer, South Dakota.
    - Mary Twedt rolling out insulation in what will be her and Dave's room, September, 1998 (Box 21, Print 75)
      They are rebuilding commercial property to make their home about 1/2 mile south of Spencer, South Dakota. (Their home in Spencer was destroyed 5-30-98). This property was once "The Golden Pheasant", a restaurant/bar connected to several small hotel rooms.
    - Danny Stone propping up the under-side insulation of a mobile home his aunt owned, early September, 1998 (Box 21, Print 76)
      She let him and Kara and Brandon (4 mo.) stay in the mobile home in Salem, South Dakota, while the Stones had their new home begin construction in Spencer.
    - Danny Stone preparing the canvas for his and Kara's wedding the following day. Veterans Park, Mitchell, South Dakota, September 18, 1998 (Box 21, Print 77)
      Danny was the main canvas worker at Spencer Canvas in Mitchell.
    - The wedding of Danny Stone and Kara Arends, Mitchell, South Dakota, September 19, 1998 (Box 21, Print 78)
      Officiating is the Reverend Ward Satterly of Spencer, South Dakota. He lost his wife in the May 30th tornado. She ran upstairs to try and save their dog as the tornado approached. The dog survived, but she perished... Kara's twin sister, Sara, pictured at right (Maid of honor).
    - Brandon Stone being prepared for his parent's wedding (Danny Stone/Kara Arends), Mitchell, South Dakota, September 19, 1998 (Box 21, Print 79)
      He was only one month old when the tornado hit. His mother, Kara Arends, hovered over him in the basement and looked up to see the house beginning to life off the foundation. Minutes later, the entire house was gone.
    - After the wedding of Jenna Webb and Cliff Carlin, in the basement of the Church of the Nazarene, Mitchell, South Dakota, October 2, 1998 (Box 21, Print 80)
      Lloyd Webb, left, and Nancy Webb holding Alexa Roth, the daughter of Vicki and Tony Roth... Vicky was a foster child who lived with the Webbs for many years.
    - Lloyd Webb power-chiseling through the concrete foundation of the farmhouse in preparation of installing a septic tank, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, October, 1998 (Box 21, Print 81)
    - Interior wall on the first floor of the Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, October, 1998 (Box 21, Print 82)
      While Nancy's parents were still living in the farmhouse, a small fire broke out. The smoke from the fire blackened the wall, leaving ghost images from ceramic birds that had been hung. Her parents left the farmhouse not long after the incident.
    - Steve, a friend of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's, constructing an addition to the back of the original family farmhouse where Nancy and her brother, Steve, and sister, Myrta, were all raised, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles norht of Spencer, October, 1998 (Box 21, Print 83)
      Lloyd, Nancy and Suzy lived in the camper trailer for several months, during construction.
    - Inside the Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, October, 1998 (Box 21, Print 84)
      The image on the left is a new downstairs bathroom/shower under construction. The image on the right is from an upstairs bedroom. The bookcase still holds books and toys from when Nancy, Myrta and Steve were children.
    - Richard Stone, during the process of installing an amplifier in his Chevy--a few miles north of Spencer at a friend's farm, McCook County, South Dakota, October, 1998 (Box 21, Print 85)
      He was basically a runaway at this point, staying with friends, cutting school.
    - A photographer from People Magazine, making images of Dave and Mary Twedt walking where their house once stood in Spencer, South Dakota before the tornado hit on 5-30-98 (Box 21, Print 86)
      (He did a page spread on the Twedts for the June, 1998 issue, visiting them just days after the tornado hit.)
    - A photographer from People Magazine, making images of Dave and Mary Twedt in front of the old Golden Pheasant Restaurant--where they are rebuilding the commercial property into a home, October 16, 1998 (Box 21, Print 87)
      The intersection of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431.
    - Mary Twedt, left, and her friend, Laura, planing hardwood floor pieces in the Twedt's basement, October, 1998 (Box 21, Print 88)
      The hardwood flooring pieces were purchased at an auction that had featured many salvaged items from the closed Spencer School (several years prior).
    - Lloyd Webb on top of the farmhouse--the day several friends from his and Nancy's church came out to help clean up, McCook County--three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, November, 1998 (Box 21, Print 89)
    - From the rooftop of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, three miles north of Spencer, mid-November, 1998 (Box 22, Print 90)
      A group of people from their church came to help do clean-up around the property.
    - Lloyd Webb grilling hamburgers and hot dogs for friends from the Church of the Nazarene (Mitchell, South Dakota) who are at the farmhouse to help with general clean-up and carpentry work, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, November, 1998 (Box 22, Print 91)
    - A free Thanksgiving dinner for the residents of Spencer, South Dakota. McCook County High School gymnasium in Salem, South Dakota (Box 22, Print 92)
      This dinner was sponsored by local businesses a few days before Thanksgiving Day, 1998.
    - Danny Stone working on his house, Thanksgiving Day, 1998 (Box 22, Print 94)
      The home builder he hired abandoned the project completely the month before, leaving the Stones with more than $35,000 debt. In other words, essentially taking $35,000 from their pockets.
    - Danny Stone with various insurance papers, Small Business Administration paperwork, building permits, etc, Spencer, South Dakota (following the 5-30-98 tornado), December 2, 1998 (Box 22, Print 95)
      The Stone's original contractor abandoned him, leaving them with about $35,000 debt. Danny had to finish the house himself.
    - Danny Stone sanding the walls and ceilings in his home, Spencer, South Dakota, December 2, 1998 (Box 22, Print 96)
      The builder he hired abandoned the job, leaving the Stones with more than $30,000 debt.
    - Lloyd Webb shoveling refuse from the newly re-built entry to the farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, the day before Thanksgiving, 1998 (Box 22, Print 97)
      He taught me how to operate the backhoe and I got pretty good at it. However, two weeks later I accidently pulled up and severed the main power lines that had recently been buried (near the center of this image). I was digging a phone line and the hired electrician was the only other person there at the time. He said folks get killed doing that sort of thing. When Nancy came home later, I admitted my mistake. She laughed and said, "Don't worry about it! Lloyd does that sort of thing all the time." I held a flashlight late into the night while the electrician repaired it.
    - Dave Twedt making his famous sign of protest (Box 22, Print 98)
      It eventually read: THE BIBLE SAYS ASK AND YOU SHALL RECEIVE SARIN SAYS BE BROKE, BE HUMILIATED, BEG, AND MAYBE WE'LL HELP WITH DONATED MONEY. SARIN (Spencer Area Recovery and Interfaith Network) was a faith-based organization headed by the Rev. Mark Dickson, pastor of the Sun Prairie Baptist Church near Salem, South Dakota. Nearly 1 million dollars was collected in donations and SARIN was responsible for distributing the funds--which they did mainly to those who were under (or not) insured. The Twedts felt this was unfair. Dave made this sign in December, 1998 and it was stolen from his property on Christmas Eve, 1998.
    - Dave Twedt applying a band-aid to his finger, Mary Twedt watching, December, 1998 (Box 22, Print 99)
      They are living in the garage area of the commercial property currently under re-construction. The "home" part of the building process will not be ready for several more weeks. They were nearly to their wit's end.
    - Mary Twedt tossing a sheet while making the bed, November 6, 1998 (Box 22, Print 100)
      She and Dave are living in the garage area of the commercial property they are remaking into a home. The "home" part of the building is under construction. Here, they were surrounded by tools Dave used to rebuild cars. The sheet makes me think of a tornado.
    - Dave Twedt being interviewed by a television reporter from Sioux City, Iowa, about his sign (on the Jeep) protesting SARIN's method of spreading money donated by the public, McCook County, South Dakota, December, 1998 (Box 22, Print 101)
      In front of his and Mary's home on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431.
    - (Left) Mary Twedt holding a photograph of the house in Spencer, South Dakota where she and her husband, Dave, lived at the time of the May 30, 1998 tornado. They were in the basement at the time. (Right) Dave Twedt holding a photograph of an 8 foot square sign he made to protest SARIN (Spencer Area Recovery and Interfaith Network), a faith based organization put in charge of allocating nearly 1 million dollars of donated money to help Spencer residents, February, 1999 (Box 22, Print 102)
      Because the Twedts were well insured, like many others, SARIN helped those who were not insured--from the very beginning. Dave felt the money should have been distributed evenly. His sign was stolen on Christmas Eve, 1998. Two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Richard Stone applying the front window license to his aunt's mobile home in Salem, South Dakota, December, 1998 (Box 22, Print 103)
      She has loaned out the use of the mobile home to Danny, Kara and their toddler, Brandon, and Richard while their new home in Spencer is under construction ten miles away.